Guide to the Leo K. Bustad Papers 1912-2005
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Leo K. Bustad Papers
1912-2005
1961-1997
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
Cage 942
Bustad, Leo K.
26.84 Linear feet of shelf space 46 Boxes
The Leo K. Bustad Papers consist of the personal and professional papers of Leo K. Bustad, the former dean of the Washington State University (WSU) College of Veterinary Medicine.
Leo K. Bustad was born in 1920 in Stanwood, Washington. He received his B.A. in Agriculture from Washington State College (now Washington State University) in 1941. Within a year of graduation, he married Signe Byrd, a Washington State College graduate in Home Economics Education, and was commissioned as a second lieutenant in the Army, serving in Italy and Germany during World War II. He returned to Pullman in 1945, after being a prisoner of war in a German prison camp for fifteen months. Dr. Bustad went on to receive his M.A. in Animal Nutrition in 1948 and his D.V.M. in 1949 from Washington State College, as well as a Ph.D. in Physiology in 1960 from the University of Washington. From 1949 to 1965, he also directed biological research at Hanford Laboratories in Benton County, Washington. He then went on to become the Director of the Radiobiology Laboratory and Comparative Oncology Laboratory at the University of California, Davis, before returning to WSU as the Dean of the College of Veterinary Medicine (1973-1983).
Dr. Bustad's research initially focused on the physiological effects of radiation exposure, but he is most widely known for spearheading the study of human-animal interaction and the human-animal bond. Among his many accomplishments and contributions to veterinary medicine, he co-founded and was the first Chair of The Delta Society (Pet Partners), also serving as its first president from 1981 to 1988. As of 2015, the society continues to present the Bustad Companion Animal Veterinarian Award to a veterinarian working in the field of human-animal interactions. Dr. Bustad founded the People-Pet Program at Washington State University, and helped establish the journal Anthrozoos (1987) on human-animal interaction studies, as well as the International Association of Human-Animal Interaction Organizations (1990). In addition to his two books (Animals, Aging, and the Aged and Compassion: Our Last Great Hope), Dr. Bustad co-authored Learning and Living Together: Building the Human-Animal Bond, and contributed to over 200 academic articles during his career.
The WSU Veterinary Science Building was renamed Bustad Hall in 1985 in honor of Dr. Bustad's service as Dean of the College of Veterinary Medicine. He remained an active member of the Pullman community until his death in 1998.
Many terms historically used to describe individuals and communities with disabilities are offensive and were used to dismiss, discount and dehumanize these individuals and communities. Terms often focused on a perceived impairment and not the person. MASC recognizes the harm caused by these terms. We retain the language in this finding aid to document history and preserve context.
The Leo K. Bustad Papers consist of the personal and professional papers of Leo K. Bustad, the former dean of the Washington State University (WSU) College of Veterinary Medicine. It includes correspondence, photographs, slides, research reports and background materials, newsletters, regional veterinary medicine education papers, materials related to The Delta Society and the human/animal bond, speeches, publications, and teaching materials, as well as audiocassettes and videocassettes by Dr. Bustad, about Dr. Bustad, and that cover his personal and professional interests. These interests include companion animals, animal-assisted therapy, veterinary curriculum, ethics and values, leadership, managing adversity, and radiobiology. The collection includes materials that postdate Dr. Bustad’s death as they relate to either him personally or to his work.
Series 1: Research, circa 1950s-1990 - This series contains both research by Dr. Bustad, as well as publications by other authors. It tends to focus on his earlier research related to radiation and includes his 1960 thesis "Physiological Response of Mice to Low Levels of Irradiation".
Subseries 1.1: Research Notes and Publications, circa 1950s-1990
Subseries 1.2: Slides, 1963-1982
Subseries 1.3: Photographs, 1966
Series 2: Professional Papers, 1912-2005 - This series spans the varied interests of Dr. Bustad’s career, including the effects of radiation, veterinary school curriculum for Washington, Idaho, and Oregon, and his work with multiple organizations related to the human-animal bond. Speeches address a variety of subjects, including compassion, ethics and values, and the benefits of the human-animal bond. Publications cover similar topics as well as document Dr. Bustad’s radiobiology work. Many publications are reprints of speeches or presentations that Dr. Bustad gave at professional conferences.
Subseries 2.1: Tri-state Shared Curriculum, 1972-1978
Subseries 2.2: The Delta Society, 1981-2001
Subseries 2.3: People-Pet Partnership, 1912-2000
Subseries 2.4: Human-Animal Bond, 1974-2005
Subseries 2.5: Washington State University, 1949-2004
Subseries 2.6: Speeches, 1961-1995
Subseries 2.7: Publications, 1948-1997
Subseries 2.8: Day Planners, 1974-1988
Subseries 2.9: Ephemera, 1954-1986
Series 3: Correspondence, 1972-2003 - This series observes Dr. Bustad’s arrangement of correspondence by general alphabetical order and specifically by person and includes correspondence with Sophie Engelhard Craighead, Dean Borje Gustafsson, and Sister Pauline Quinn.
Subseries 3.1: General Correspondence, 1974-1977
Subseries 3.2: Correspondence by Person, 1972-2003
Series 4: Personal Papers, 1930s-1997 - This series includes photographs, certificates and honors, newspaper clippings, Christmas letters, curriculum vitae, memorial service notes, paperwork related to Dr. Bustad’s retirement from the United States Army, and other personal materials. This series contains restricted materials.
Series 5: Audiovisual Materials, 1962-1998 - This series contains multiple formats related to Dr. Bustad’s professional and personal interests, including the human-animal bond, animal behavior, animal-assisted therapy, veterinary medicine and research, and ethics and values. Materials are by Dr. Bustad as well as by others.
Subseries 5.1: Reel to Reel, 1962-1969
Subseries 5.2: U-matics, circa 1980s (many undated)
Subseries 5.3: VHS cassettes, 1972-1998 (many undated)
Subseries 5.4: Audiocassettes, 1972-1994 (many undated)
This collection is arranged in 5 series; where possible, Dr. Bustad’s arrangement and folder titles are retained. Correspondence is in Bustad's original general alphabetical order and specifically by person.
This collection is open and available for research use, with exception of certain personally identifiable information and protected health information in Series 4. Where possible, personally identifiable information has been redacted, with the original documents segregated in restricted folders. Protected health information is restricted until 2073.
The Washington State University (WSU) Libraries received this collection in multiple installments. The WSU Health Sciences Libraries transferred materials between 1997 and 2009 (MS.1997.24, MS.1999.11, MS.2008.19, MS.2008.27, and MS.2009.07). In addition, the WSU College of Veterinary Medicine transferred additional materials in 2017 (MS.2017.04) and 2018 (MS.2018.07).
The repository expects to receive additions to this collection.
Documents with personally identifiable information have been segregated to restricted folders. Redacted versions of the documents are available for research.
In addition to Dr. Bustad’s papers, Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections (MASC) received a number of books owned by Dr. Bustad. These were primarily used by Dr. Bustad for his thesis and will be catalogued and made available to researchers in MASC.
Veterinary Medicine College Records, 1932-1975 (Archives 21)
Veterans Oral History Interviews, 1996-2009 (Archives 232)
Veterinary Medicine College Associate Dean Records, 1976-1978 (Archives 177)
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Bustad, Leo K. -- Archives
Washington State University -- Faculty -- Archives
Veterinarians -- United States -- Archives; Veterinary medicine--United States
Science; Colleges and Universities
- Series 1: Research
  This series contains both research by Dr. Bustad, as well as publications by other authors. It tends to focus on his earlier research related to radiation and includes his 1960 thesis "Physiological Response of Mice to Low Levels of Irradiation".
  - Subseries 1.1: Research Notes and Publications
    - Beta radiation of skin experment:papers circa 1950s-1960s (Folder 1, Item 1)
    - Skin diffuser studies, 1950s-1960s (Folder 1, Item 2)
    - Skin studies (1 of 3), 1950s-1960s (Folder 1, Item 3)
    - Skin studies (2 of 3), 1950s-1960s (Folder 1, Item 4)
    - Skin studies (3 of 3), 1960 (Folder 1, Item 5)
    - Radiation courses (1 of 2), circa 1950s-1960s (Folder 1, Item 6)
    - Radiation courses (2 of 2), circa 1950s-1960s (Folder 1, Item 7)
    - Copy of letter to Dr. Albert Schweitzer from Willard F. Libby, Atomic Energy Commissioner, 1957 (Folder 1, Item 8)
    - UK Ministry of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food: Agricultural Defense Training Report, 1964 (Folder 1, Item 9)
    - UK Ministry of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food: A.R.O Papers, 1962-1964 (Folder 1, Item 10)
    - Pigs in the Laboratory 1966/Thyroid Function in Domestic Animals reprints, 1970 (Folder 1, Item 11)
    - Dose and Dose Rate Problems in Radiation Tumorigenesis, 1975 (Folder 1, Item 12)
    - A Comparative Study of Hanford and Utah Range Sheep, 1953 (Folder 1, Item 13)
    - Damage to Livestock from Radioactive Fallout in Nuclear War Draft #5, 1962 (Folder 1, Item 14)
    - The Contribution of Pets to Human Development: A Review of the Literature from the Social Sciences Portraying the Role of Pets in Society, 1977 February (Folder 1, Item 15)
    - Sheep Deaths in Utah and Nevada Following the 1953 Nuclear Tests, 1979 (Folder 1, Item 16)
    - "Sheep case", 1980 (Folder 1, Item 17)
    - The Companion Animal Semantic Differential: Long and Short Form Reliability and Validity, 1988 (Folder 1, Item 18)
    - New Osteological and C-isotope Evidence on Mesolithic Dogs: Companions to Hunters and Fishers at Star Carr, Seamer Carr, and Kongemose, 1990 (Folder 1, Item 19)
    - Bound Thesis by Leo K. Bustad - Physiological Responses of Mice to Low Levels of Irradiation, 1960 (Folder 2, Item 20)
    - Bound Thesis by Leo K. Bustad - Physiological Responses of Mice to Low Levels of Irradiation - handwritten first page, 1960 (Folder 2, Item 21)
    - "L.K.B. thesis studies" - Ionizing Radiation Studies on Mice: Final Report on Contract AT (45-1) 1094 between the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission and the University of Washington, 1964 December 30 (Folder 2, Item 22)
    - "Seminars", 1972 (Folder 2, Item 23)
  - Subseries 1.2: Slides
    - Irradiated Cow Udder, 1966 (Folder 3, Item 24)
    - Iodine, 1966-1971 (Folder 3, Item 25)
    - Marmosa, 1968 (Folder 3, Item 26)
    - General, 1968-1971 (Folder 3, Item 27)
    - Federal veterinarians, 1973-1980 (Folder 3, Item 28)
    - Mice, undated (Folder 3, Item 29)
    - Custom made, undated (Folder 3, Item 30)
    - Miscellaneous, 1967 (Folder 3, Item 31)
    - Radium, undated (Folder 3, Item 32)
    - Skin, 1965-1967 (Folder 3, Item 33)
    - Dogs and SR-90, 1963-1968 (Folder 3, Item 34)
    - Effects 90 Sr, 1969 (Folder 3, Item 35)
    - Eye, 1966-1972 (Folder 3, Item 36)
    - Main study, 1968-1969 (Folder 3, Item 37)
    - Experimental subjects and animal models, 1967-1969 (Folder 4, Item 38)
    - Computer technology, undated (Folder 4, Item 39)
    - Curriculum, 1964-1978 (Folder 4, Item 40)
    - Cytogenetics, undated (Folder 4, Item 41)
    - Embryo transplants, 1971-1980 (Folder 4, Item 42)
    - Energy, power crisis and nuclear power, 1972 (Folder 4, Item 43)
    - Facilities and other experiments, 1968-1977 (Folder 4, Item 44)
    - Facilities radiobiology lab, 1965-1979 (Folder 4, Item 45)
    - Plutonium, undated (Folder 4, Item 46)
    - Radiation effects, 1972 (Folder 4, Item 47)
    - Radiation effects logistics, undated (Folder 5, Item 48)
    - X-rad dogs, undated (Folder 5, Item 49)
    - X-rad monkey, undated (Folder 5, Item 50)
    - X-rad mice, undated (Folder 5, Item 51)
    - Veterinary medicine, undated (Folder 5, Item 52)
    - Oregon, 1981 (Folder 5, Item 53)
    - Animals, 1976-1981 (Folder 5, Item 54)
    - Facilities, 1978 (Folder 5, Item 55)
    - General research, 1978-1987 (Folder 5, Item 56)
    - Animals, aging and the aged, undated (Folder 5, Item 57)
    - Ash-Hooper, 1980-1981 (Folder 5, Item 58)
    - Animal disease, undated (Folder 5, Item 59)
    - Biohazards, undated (Folder 5, Item 60)
    - Bone, 1988 (Folder 5, Item 61)
    - Cancer, 1968-1973 (Folder 5, Item 62)
    - Captions, charts and graphs, undated (Folder 5, Item 63)
    - Radiation, undated (Folder 5, Item 64)
    - Diseased animals, 1969-1981 (Folder 5, Item 65)
    - Facilities, 1973-1982 (Folder 5, Item 66)
    - Facilities and experiments, 1964-1979 (Folder 6, Item 67)
    - Veterinary medicine, undated (Folder 6, Item 68)
    - Health, animals and people, undated (Folder 6, Item 69)
    - Wise words, undated (Folder 6, Item 70)
    - Black, undated (Folder 6, Item 71)
    - Charts and comparisons, undated (Folder 6, Item 72)
    - Fallout, undated (Folder 6, Item 73)
    - Iodine or Thyroid, 1967-1968 (Folder 6, Item 74)
    - Toxicology, undated (Folder 6, Item 75)
    - Medicine and nuclear physics, 1972 (Folder 6, Item 76)
    - University of California Davis, RBL, 1968-1973 (Folder 6, Item 77)
    - Pigs, 1967-1975 (Folder 6, Item 78)
    - Hiroshima, 1966 (Folder 7, Item 79)
    - Teaching, 1968-1972 (Folder 7, Item 80)
  - Subseries 1.3: Photographs
    - Scientific American/Pigs in the Laboratory ( 1 of 2), 1966 (Folder 7, Item 81)
    - Scientific American/Pigs in the Laboratory ( 2 of 2), 1966 (Folder 7, Item 82)
    - Pigs in the Laboratory, 1966 (Folder 7, Item 83)
    - Ewe, dog experiments; laboratory, undated (Folder 7, Item 84)
    - Radiation, undated (Folder 7, Item 85)
- Series 2: Professional Papers
  This series spans the varied interests of Dr. Bustad’s career, including the effects of radiation, veterinary school curriculum for Washington, Idaho, and Oregon, and his work with multiple organizations related to the human-animal bond. Speeches address a variety of subjects, including compassion, ethics and values, and the benefits of the human-animal bond. Publications cover similar topics as well as document Dr. Bustad’s radiobiology work. Many publications are reprints of speeches or presentations that Dr. Bustad gave at professional conferences.
  - Subseries 2.1: Tri-state Shared Curriculum
    - Tri-state shared curriculum, 1973-1974 (Folder 8, Item 86)
    - Task force to study shared curriculum, 1974-1975 (Folder 8, Item 87)
    - Task force to study shared curriculum, 1975-1976 (Folder 8, Item 88)
    - General (1 of 6), 1972-1976 (Folder 8, Item 89)
    - General (2 of 6), 1972-1976 (Folder 8, Item 90)
    - General (3 of 6), 1972-1976 (Folder 9, Item 91)
    - General (4 of 6), 1972-1976 (Folder 9, Item 92)
    - General (5 of 6), 1972-1976 (Folder 9, Item 93)
    - General (6 of 6), 1972-1976 (Folder 9, Item 94)
    - Interim Report: Planning and Development of a Method and Procedure for Implementing a Regionally Shared Curriculum in Veterinary Medicine, 1974 July 01-1975 October 31 (Folder 9, Item 95)
    - Second Quarterly Report: Planning and Development of a Method and Procedure for Implementing a Regionally Shared Curriculum in Veterinary Medicine, 1975 February 28 (Folder 9, Item 96)
    - Interim Report: Planning and Development of a Method and Procedure for Implementing a Regionally Shared Curriculum in Veterinary Medicine, 1976 February 14-1976 May 15 (Folder 10, Item 97)
    - Final Report: Planning and Development of a Method and Procedure for Implementing a Regionally Shared Curriculum in Veterinary Medicine, 1976 September 30 (Folder 10, Item 98)
    - Final Report: Demonstration Project for Implementation of a Regional Curriculum in Veterinary Medical Education Utilizing Resources from Several States, 1978 June 30 (Folder 10, Item 99)
    - Oregon proposals, 1974-1976 (Folder 10, Item 100)
    - Oregon proposals, 1975-1976 (Folder 10, Item 101)
    - Oregon proposals, 1974-1975 (Folder 10, Item 102)
    - Oregon proposals, 1973-1974 (Folder 11, Item 103)
    - Oregon proposals, 1975-1976 (Folder 11, Item 104)
    - Oregon proposals, 1974 (Folder 11, Item 105)
    - Regional Approach to Provide Veterinary Medical Educational Opportunities and Veterinarians in Oregon, 1976 November 23 (Folder 11, Item 106)
    - Idaho proposals, 1974 (Folder 11, Item 107)
    - Idaho proposals (1 of 2), 1973-1976 (Folder 11, Item 108)
    - Idaho proposals (2 of 2), 1973-1976 (Folder 12, Item 109)
  - Subseries 2.2: The Delta Society
    - International Conference on the Human-Animal Bond, 1981 (Folder 12, Item 110)
    - WSU Veterinary News: Delta and the DVM by Dr. Bustad, 1981 November (Folder 12, Item 111)
    - The Delta Society board of directors manual, 1981 (Folder 12, Item 112)
    - Delta Society board meeting minutes, 1981-1996 (Folder 12, Item 113)
    - History of The Delta Society (1 of 2), 1981-1982 (Folder 12, Item 114)
    - History of The Delta Society (2 of 2), 1984-1995 (Folder 12, Item 115)
    - The Delta Society Newsletter, 1982 July (Folder 12, Item 116)
    - The Delta Society board briefings, 1983 September (Folder 12, Item 117)
    - The Delta Society annual meeting, 1983 (Folder 13, Item 118)
    - The Journal of The Delta Society Volume 1, Number 1, 1984 Fall (Folder 13, Item 119)
    - The Interaction of People, Animals and the Environment international meeting, 1984 (Folder 13, Item 120)
    - The Pet Connection: Proceedings of the Minnesota-California Conferences on the Human-Animal Bond, 1984 (Folder 13, Item 121)
    - Conference on Interaction of People, Animals and the Environment, 1985 (Folder 13, Item 122)
    - Newspaper clippings: Dr. Bustad and The Delta Society, 1985-1989 (Folder 13, Item 123)
    - The Delta Society international conference, 1986 (Folder 13, Item 124)
    - The Delta Society: a 1986 overview (Folder 13, Item 125)
    - Chapter manual for The Delta Society, first edition, 1986 December (Folder 13, Item 126)
    - Interactions of People, Animals and the Environment conference newsletter, 1986-1988 (Folder 13, Item 127)
    - The Delta Society board of directors information manual (1 of 2), 1982-1988 (Folder 13, Item 128)
    - The Delta Society board of directors information manual (2 of 2), 1982-1988 (Folder 13, Item 129)
    - Draft and related documents for the presentation by Vaughan, Larson and Ryan at The Delta Society, Vancouver, British Columbia, 1987 (Folder 13, Item 130)
    - Delta Society 7th conference, 1988 (Folder 13, Item 131)
    - About The Delta Society, 1988 (Folder 13, Item 132)
    - Delta publication name change, 1988 (Folder 13, Item 133)
    - Delta 1988 pre-campaign study (Folder 13, Item 134)
    - Animal veterinary award winner Strimple, 1988 (Folder 13, Item 135)
    - 1989 winner of the Bustad Companion Animal Veterinarian Award James Harris (Folder 13, Item 136)
    - Delta Society 8th conference, 1989 (Folder 13, Item 137)
    - Animal-assisted therapy implementation service, 1989 (Folder 13, Item 138)
    - Delta Society campaign, 1989-1991 (Folder 13, Item 139)
    - 1990 Bustad Companion Animal Veterinarian Award (Folder 13, Item 140)
    - Acceptance of The Delta Society Distinguished Service Award, 1990 (Folder 13, Item 141)
    - Canine good citizen test, 1990 (Folder 13, Item 142)
    - Delta Society 9th annual conference, 1990 (Folder 13, Item 143)
    - Grants, 1990 (Folder 14, Item 144)
    - Macarthur Foundation, 1990 February (Folder 14, Item 145)
    - International Council on Human-Animal Interactions, 1990 (Folder 14, Item 146)
    - Delta board members "crisis", 1991 (Folder 14, Item 147)
    - Terry Ryan - Hills Pet Products, 1991 (Folder 14, Item 148)
    - The Delta Society board of directors manual (1 of 2), 1992 (Folder 14, Item 149)
    - The Delta Society board of directors manual (2 of 2), 1992 (Folder 14, Item 150)
    - Director's report to the board, 1992 Spring (Folder 14, Item 151)
    - International Conference on the Relationship between Humans and Animals Montreal, 1992 (Folder 14, Item 152)
    - Delta Society 12th annual conference, 1993 (Folder 14, Item 153)
    - Delta Society 1993 overview (Folder 14, Item 154)
    - Various newspaper/magazine articles 1993 Delta awards (Folder 14, Item 155)
    - Delta 1993 financial report (Folder 14, Item 156)
    - Delta 1993-1994 budget (Folder 14, Item 157)
    - Delta references on human-animal bond, 1994 (Folder 14, Item 158)
    - Delta Society/The Caring Communique, 1994-1995 (Folder 14, Item 159)
    - Delta 1995 case statement (Folder 14, Item 160)
    - Delta: An Overview 1995 (Folder 14, Item 161)
    - Delta strategic planning, 1993-1996 (Folder 14, Item 162)
    - Sophie Engelhard Craighead Center dedication, 1996 (Folder 15, Item 163)
    - Singlehurst, Delta president, 1996 (Folder 15, Item 164)
    - Revised bylaws, 1996 (Folder 15, Item 165)
    - Delta Society 1996 program activities and directions (Folder 15, Item 166)
    - Delta Society pet loss resources 1998 inscription (Folder 15, Item 167)
    - Delta Society 1996 conference, 1998 (Folder 15, Item 168)
    - Delta Society affiliate, 1999 (Folder 15, Item 169)
    - Animal-assisted therapy in schools book, 1999 (Folder 15, Item 170)
    - Delta curriculum advertisement, 1999 (Folder 15, Item 171)
    - Linda and Donald Hines, 1983-1999 (Folder 15, Item 172)
    - Delta evaluator, 2001 (Folder 15, Item 173)
    - Delta Society Annual Report, 2001 (Folder 15, Item 174)
    - Delta legal aspects (1 of 2), 1983-1989 (Folder 15, Item 175)
    - Delta legal aspects (1 of 2), 1983-1989 (Folder 15, Item 176)
    - Professional Standard for Dog Trainers: Effective, Humane Principles, 2001 (Folder 16, Item 177)
    - Board code of ethics, undated (Folder 16, Item 178)
    - Delta Society program guidelines, undated (Folder 16, Item 179)
    - Delta graphics, undated (Folder 16, Item 180)
    - Delta Society promotional materials, undated (Folder 16, Item 181)
    - The Delta Society - for pet set, undated (Folder 16, Item 182)
    - Hearing Dog Resource Center, undated (Folder 16, Item 183)
  - Subseries 2.3: People-Pet Partnership
    - People-Pet Partnership Learning and Living Together: Building the Human-Animal Bond, 1986 (Folder 16, Item 184)
    - People-Pet Partnership approved by Delta for affiliate membership, 1991 (Folder 16, Item 185)
    - Pet Partners Program Newsletter, 1991-1995 (Folder 16, Item 186)
    - Pound Puppies promotional coloring book, 1995 (Folder 16, Item 187)
    - Pet Partners program, 1992-2000 (Folder 16, Item 188)
    - Pet Partners workshops, undated (Folder 16, Item 189)
    - Sample bibliography on animal-facilitated therapy, undated (Folder 16, Item 190)
    - Slides People-Pet Partnership Program, 1982 (Folder 16, Item 191)
    - Slides People-Pet Partnership Program Dr. Bustad, 1978-1990 (Folder 16, Item 192)
    - Slides People-Pet Partnership Program comp. medicine, 1979-1990 (Folder 16, Item 193)